Finding Aid for Alice and Jessie Bourquin Papers 1905-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alice and Jessie Bourquin papers
1905-1991
Bourquin, Alice, 1909-1995.
Landscape designers based in Ann Arbor, Michigan. Planting and landscape plans, elevation drawings, and various other sketches for projects designed as students at the University of Michigan and subsequently for clients in Ann Arbor, Michigan and other residences in southeastern Michigan; files relating to Jessie Bourquin's work with the Michigan Department of Economic Expansion and Alice Bourquin's work with the Michigan Department of Transportation; also papers relating to joint projects and activities, including their association with Jens Jensen and their Hillwood subdivision in Ann Arbor; and photographs.
93802 Aa 2; Ac
7 linear feet
1 oversize folders
19 folders
1 tubes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Many of the architectural drawings were donated by Michelle Bentley (Donor no. 7764 ) and came to the library through the University of Michigan University Architect's Office in January 1990. Other materials came from the Bourquin family (donor no. 7764 ) in 2000.
The collection is open for research.
Twins Alice and Jessie Bourquin were born in Muskegon, Michigan in 1909. Their father James, president of Continental Motors, moved the family to Grosse Pointe the next year. At his death in 1923 the Bourquins moved to Hillwood, the family property in Ann Arbor which had been used on week-ends and vacations. Alice and Jessie attended the University of Michigan, taking classes in languages, the arts, and literature while earning teaching certificates in French. A course in landscape design taught by Aubrey Tealdi appealed to their love of art and nature, inspiring them to take city planning courses at the Sorbonne in Paris after graduation and to earn master's degrees in landscape design from the University of Michigan in 1934.
They began a private landscape design practice in Ann Arbor that same year, but found clients scarce due to the Depression. Beginning in 1935 Alice went to work for the State Highway Department in Lansing. The first woman landscape architect hired by the highway department, she did not let minority status deter her, but went on to a 39-year career which involved assisting in the design of most of the 103 roadside parks on the Michigan state highway system. Jessie Bourquin carried on the landscape design practice alone for five years, then joined her sister in Lansing, where she went to work for the Michigan Department of Commerce as an economic research analyst. The Bourquins lived together in Lansing, retired together in 1974, and returned to the family property in Ann Arbor.
Beginning in the 1930s the sisters and their brother James had begun to subdivide and develop the family acreage on Geddes Avenue near the Arboretum. By the 1960s four subdivisions, Hillwood I-IV, had been constructed. After their retirement the Bourquins began the last phase of development on 25 hilly, wooded acres, maintaining the strict building and use restrictions which had served to preserve privacy and natural beauty throughout the property. All Hillwood residents become members of the nonprofit Hillwood Community Preserve Association, and all building exteriors, siting, and tree-cutting had to be approved by the Bourquins.
For their 80th birthdays the American Society of Landscape Architects sponsored a party for the Bourquin sisters, who also received certificates of appreciation from Governor James Blanchard and the Michigan House and Senate. They continued to live on Hillwood into the 1990s in their 1985-designed "dream house."
Beyond their professional lives, the twins enjoyed traveling around the United States and Europe. Neither sister ever married. Alice passed away in 1995 with Jessie following in 1999.
The Bourquin collection consists of landscape architectural drawings, professional papers, and visual materials documenting the careers of Alice and Jessie Bourquin. The collection has been divided into the following series: Landscape Architectural Drawings; Jessie Bourquin Papers; Alice Bourquin Papers; Joint Projects and Activities; Hillwood Subdivision; and Photographs and other Visual Materials.
Subjects:
American Society of Landscape Architects.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Bourquin, Alice, 1909-1995.; Bourquin, Jessie, 1909-1999.; Gardens--Design.; Hillwood (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Landscape architects--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Landscape architecture--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Martha Cook building.; Michigan. Dept. of Economic Expansion.; Michigan. Dept. of Transportation.; Roads--Michigan.; Roadside improvement--Michigan.; Roadside rest areas--Michigan.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Design.; Women landscape architects--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Bourquin, Alice, 1909-1995.; Bourquin, Jessie, 1909-1999.; Gardens--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Hillwood (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Landscape architectural drawings.; University of Michigan. Martha Cook building.; National socialism and architecture.; Twins.
Contributors:
Bourquin, Alice, 1909-1995.; Bourquin, Jessie, 1909-1999.; Jensen, Jens, 1860-1951.
Genre/Form:
Albums.; Architectural drawings.; Landscape architectural drawing.; Photographs.
- Landscape architectural drawings
  The landscape architectural drawings series documents the sisters' Ann Arbor-based landscape design practice begun in the 1930s. This series begins with some of their student projects from graduate school at the University of Michigan followed by commissions in Ann Arbor (mainly in the 1930s and 1940s), several later design commissions from the 1940s after they had relocated to Lansing, and finally with a subseries of landscape projects undertaken for the Michigan Highway Department.
  Pencil and watercolor on heavyweight paper were used for most of the Student Projects from the early 1930s. This subseries consists of plans and elevation drawings for public facilities, including a teahouse, an automobile club, a military entrance, and a roadside market. Also part of this subseries are two pencil-drawn plans for a residential district of a city and two colored drawings of a playground park plan. Some of the drawings are signed by Alice or Jessie; others are not, but are obviously by the same hand(s).
  The bulk of the series is made up of two subseries of landscape project drawings for a number of Michigan clients in the 1930s and 1940s; one subseries documents commissions within Ann Arbor, the other covers Michigan Projects outside of the city. These drawings include general landscape plans, detailed planting plans, building elevation drawings, and some plans and sketches for garden structures such as rose arbors, summer houses, and pools. The formats include pencil drawings on tracing paper, photocopies of such drawings, and blueprints. There is some duplication of drawings in different formats.
  Some projects are fully documented by several drawings, while others consist of only one plan. Most of the work is by Jessie Bourquin, who carried on the practice alone after Alice relocated to Lansing in 1935. The finely detailed plans and beautifully executed drawings attest to a high level of professional skill, as well as to the assiduous attention to detail for which the Bourquins became known. Intricate planting plans include dozens of varieties of flowers, trees, and shrubs arranged in multiple beds.
  In addition to illustrating the sisters' professional capabilities, the Bourquins' drawings help to document the "end of an era" in Ann Arbor and other communities -- the decline of the leisured, aristocratic estate lifestyle of the well-to-do in early twentieth century America. The Bourquins ended their practice and sought new careers as the Depression dampened demand for luxuries like landscaping, and after World War II different, less elaborate architectural tastes came to the fore.
  - Student Projects, 1932-1934
    - Roadside market sketches and plans (Map-case 226, Folder 1)
    - Automobile club sketches and plans (Map-case 226, Folder 1)
    - Residential district plans (Map-case 226, Folder 1)
    - Playground park plans (Map-case 226, Folder 1)
    - Tea house sketches and plans (Map-case 226, Folder 1)
    - Entrance for a military cemetery sketch (Map-case 226, Folder 1)
    - Villa Lante plan (Map-case 226, Folder 1)
    - Landscape plan for Mrs. John Bentley (Map-case 226, Folder 1)
    - Golf course subdivision plan (Map-case 226, Folder 2)
    - Detroit recreational park plans (Map-case 226, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Map-case 226, Folder 2)
  - Ann Arbor Projects, 1934-1971; 1934-1941
    - Alexander Ruthven, 1934; 1937-1938 (Map-case 226, Folder 3)
    - Mrs. Alex Dow 1935, 1938 "Brushwood" (Barton Hills) (Map-case 226, Folder 4)
    - Mrs. Mary Church, 1937 (Map-case 226, Folder 5)
    - Professor Clifford Woody, 1937 (Map-case 226, Folder 5)
    - Mrs. R.B. Canfield, 1937 (Map-case 226, Folder 5)
    - Dr. Bradley Patten, 1937 (Map-case 226, Folder 5)
    - Misses Hinsdale, 1937 (Map-case 226, Folder 5)
    - Drs. Bert and Beth Heberer, 1937 (Map-case 226, Folder 5)
    - U-M Press Building (Map-case 226, Folder 5)
    - Dr. and Mrs. Edgar A. Kahn, 1949 (Map-case 226, Folder 5)
    - Mr. and Mrs. R. S. McNamara, 1949 (Map-case 226, Folder 5)
    - Ernest Evans, 1937 (Map-case 226, Folder 6)
    - Dr. Paul Barker, 1937-1938 (Map-case 226, Folder 6)
    - Bruce Fralick, 1937-1938 (Map-case 226, Folder 6)
    - Dr. Malcolm Soule, 1938 (Map-case 88, Folder 7)
    - Dr. John Alexander, 1939 (Map-case 88, Folder 7)
    - University of Michigan Martha Cook Dormitory, 1938 (Map-case 88, Folder 7)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Leroy Weir, 1940 (Map-case 88, Folder 8)
    - Mrs. H. H. Seeley, 1940 (Map-case 88, Folder 8)
    - Dr. Karl Malcolm, 1940-1941 (Map-case 88, Folder 8)
    - Mrs. F. C. Karl, 1943 (Map-case 88, Folder 8)
    - Sigma Phi, 1964 (Map-case 88, Folder 9)
    - Hilldene Manor, 1947 (Map-case 88, Folder 9)
    - Mrs. Walter Prochnow, 1938 (Map-case 88, Folder 9)
    - First Methodist Church, 1940 (Map-case 88, Folder 9)
    - Dr. and Mrs. Albert C. Furstenberg, 1951 (Map-case 88, Folder 9)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Arjay R. Miller, 1951 (Map-case 88, Folder 9)
    - Mrs. Carl Badgley, 1938 (Map-case 88, Folder 9)
    - Gamma Phi Beta, 1945 (Map-case 88, Folder 9)
    - Hillwood Subdivision, 1953-1971 (scattered) (Map-case 88, Folder 10, 10-a)
    - Glendale on the Parkway plans, 1912 (Tube 1)
      Olmsted Bros. project in Ann Arbor on the same site as the later Hillwood project of the Bourquins
  - Michigan Projects Outside Of Ann Arbor, 1935-1949
    - Mrs. Louis Mendelssohn (Grosse Pointe Shores), 1935 (Map-case 89, Folder 11)
    - Covert Robertson (Pleasant Ridge), 1936 (Map-case 89, Folder 11)
    - Glenn Pickett (East Lansing), 1936 (Map-case 89, Folder 11)
    - Mr. Boughton (Maceday Lake, Oakland County) (Map-case 89, Folder 11)
    - Dr. J. J. Woods (Ypsilanti), 1941 (Map-case 89, Folder 11)
    - D.W. Martin (Ypsilanti), 1941 (Map-case 89, Folder 11)
    - James W. Macmeekin (Saginaw), 1949 (Map-case 89, Folder 11)
    - O. E. Robbins (Dearborn), 1941 (Map-case 89, Folder 12)
    - Max Whitmore (Okemos), 1948 (Map-case 89, Folder 12)
    - R.C. Whitmore (Indian Hills subdivision), 1947 (Map-case 89, Folder 12)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Claud R. Erickson (Lansing), 1949 (Map-case 89, Folder 13)
    - Mr. and Mrs. A.E. Summerfield (Flint), 1941 (Map-case 89, Folder 13)
    - Mr. and Mrs. M. Davison, Jr. (Flint), 1946 (Map-case 89, Folder 13)
    - Methodist Home (Chelsea)., 1942 (Map-case 89, Folder 13)
    - City of Port Huron sewage and garbage treatment plant, 1945 (Map-case 89, Folder 13)
    - City of Niles sewage treatment plant, 1949 (Map-case 89, Folder 13)
    - Briggs Co. (St. Johns), 1948 (Map-case 89, Folder 13)
    - Mrs. G.L. Buhrman (Mullet Lake), undated (Map-case 89, Folder 13)
    - Proposed Garden of the Nations, undated (Map-case 89, Folder 13)
    - Mackenzie Manor Housing (Detroit), 1939 (Map-case 89, Folder 13)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Donald Nash (Saginaw), 1941 (Map-case 89, Folder 13-A)
  - Highway Department Landscape Projects, 1930s-1960s (scattered)
    - Near Willow Run Bomber plant (Map-case 89, Folder 14)
    - Edsel Ford Expressway, circa 1950 (Map-case 89, Folder 14)
    - Muskegon (Nunica-Muskegon Rd.; US 16 & 31 business Rte.), 1962 (Map-case 89, Folder 15)
    - Jackson-North Belt, 1949 (Map-case 89, Folder 15)
    - Flight strip area (Lake Huron between Port Austin and Caseville) (Map-case 89, Folder 15)
    - Alpena-Rogers City Rd. (US 23 roadside park), 1941 (Map-case 89, Folder 15)
    - Typical roadside rest area (Map-case 89, Folder 16)
    - Playground park (Fowlerville), 1949 (Map-case 89, Folder 16)
    - Cut River area (U.S. 2, Mackinac County), 1947 (Map-case 89, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous roadside park plans (Map-case 89, Folder 16)
    - Three Rivers-Jackson Road (roadside park, M-60), 1936 (Map-case 89, Folder 17)
    - Detroit-Pontiac Rd. (Woodward Ave., Birmingham), 1941 (Map-case 89, Folder 17)
    - Marquette-Michigamme Road (roadside park, M-28), 1939 (Map-case 89, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous (Map-case 89, Folder 17)
- Jessie Bourquin Papers, 1942-1978
  The Jessie Bourquin series focuses primarily on her work with the Michigan Department of Economic Expansion, including pamphlets, memos, research, reports, and correspondence. Also documented is Jessie's involvement with the American Association of Landscape Architects and her private landscaping career.
  - Personal, Academic, and Career Papers, 1942-1972 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Department of Economic Development
    - Research, Fact Sheets, and Memos, 1947-1972; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Reports, 1951-1959; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Research Papers, 1949-1967 (Box 1)
    - Memos and Clippings, 1956-1965 (Box 1)
    - Incoming Correspondence, 1959-1966 (Box 1)
    - Articles in French on Michigan, 1965-1978 (Box 1)
  - American Society of Landscape Architects
    - Brochure Committee, 1952-1954 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and Meeting Notes, 1955-1956 (Box 1)
    - National Civil Service Committee, 1958-1960 (Box 1)
- Alice Bourquin Papers, 1930s-1981
  The Alice Bourquin series documents Alice's work for her master's degree, as well as miscellaneous correspondence, landscape drawings, and various newspaper clippings. As with her sister, the bulk of this series is focused on her work for the Michigan Department of Transportation and involvement with the American Society of Landscape Architects.
  - Papers Written for Master's Degree Courses, 1930s (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1935-1982 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1960-1967 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Department of Transportation
    - Position Description, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Newsletters and Pamphlets, 1951-1980 (Box 1)
    - Landscape Cost Studies, 1934-1940 (Box 1)
    - Projects, 1938-1943; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Awards, 1961-1981 (Box 1)
  - American Society of Landscape Architects Committee on Highways, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Agricultural Conservation Program, 1968 (Box 1)
- Joint Projects and Activities, 1905; 1925-1991
  The Joint Projects and Activities series deals with many different areas of both the professional and retirement sides of Jessie and Alice Bourquin. Contained here is the correspondence with architect Jens Jensen, projects of their private practice, and documentation of their involvement with the American Association of Landscape Architects and the International Federation of Landscape Architects.
  - Jessie Phillips (mother) U-M Graduation Program, 1905 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1933-1935 (Box 1)
  - Jens Jensen Correspondence and Articles, 1933-1935 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1937-1950 (Box 1)
  - Recreational County Guide and Nature Trail, Master's Project, 1934; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Private Practice, 1925-1964 (Box 2)
  - Beta Delta House, 1951 (Box 2)
  - 1st Congregational Church, Ann Arbor, 1952-1976 (Box 2)
  - Letters of Recommendation, 1942-1950 (Box 2)
  - American Society of Landscape Architects Application Materials and Correspondence, 1947-1951 (Box 2)
  - International Federation of Landscape Architects, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Lilianne Fumey Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - Travel Reminisces, undated (Box 2)
  - Overview of Careers, 1988-1991 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Resolution to Honor Jessie and Alice Bourquin, 1981 (Folder Ac)
  - Membership Certificates to the American Society of Landscape Architects, MCML (Folder Ac)
  - Genealogy (Folder Ac)
- Hillwood, 1911-1983
  The Hillwood series details the Bourquin sisters' work on their subdivision project during their careers and following their retirement. This Hillwood series focuses on facets of such an enterprise, including legal, realty, and contracting documentation. Site plans and other drawings are located in the Landscape Architectural Drawings series.
  - Atwell Hicks Surveyors, Civil Engineers; Planners, Al Suggitt, 1931-1974 (Box 2)
  - Deeds and Quit Claims for Bourquin Property, 1931-1952 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings promoting Hillwood, 1939-1951 (Box 2)
  - A Subdivision Guide for Preparing Plats in Township Areas of Washtenaw County, October 9, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1956 (Box 2)
  - Subdivision Upkeep, 1968-1981 (Box 2)
  - Realty
    - Initial Development Discussion, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - Feasibility Studies of Bourquin Property, 1972 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1969-1982 (Box 2)
  - Subdivision No. 5
    - General Plan, July 1953 (Box 2)
    - Road Grading, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Deeds of Sale, 1976-1977; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Atwell Hicks, Surveyors, Civil Engineers; Planners, Al Suggitt, 1975-1983; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1981 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1974-1977 (Box 2)
    - Restrictions for Huntington Woods, undated (Box 2)
  - Legal
    - Abstract Deed and Title to Bourquin, 1911 (Box 2)
    - State Land Development Forms, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Contracts I and II, Reconstruction of Rock Creek Drive, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Quit Claim Deed #3, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Woodland Subdivision Development, 1973-1976 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1973-1980; 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Photographs and other visual materials, 1905-1980 (scattered); 1.25 linear feet
  The Photographs and other visual materials series (1910-1941; 1.25 linear feet) documents the Bourquins from babyhood through their early career and includes albums of their travels to Florida and Europe, as well as professional folio prints of Jessie's private work for such notables as Alexander Dow and former University of Michigan President Alexander Ruthven. Also of interest are the various candid shots of Michigan and Ann Arbor landscaping and gardening in the 1930s. Included are photos of National Socialist architecture accumulated by their brother James Bourqin during his wartime service.
  - Jessie Bourquin
    - Ann Arbor Garden Pictures, 1934 (Box 3)
    - Frederick Dow Garden, 1939 (Box 3)
    - Edsel Ford Estate, undated (Box 3)
    - Huron Nature Trail, undated (Box 3)
    - Huron-Clinton Project, undated (Box 3)
    - Gardens, undated (Box 3)
    - Landscape Photos, undated (Box 3)
    - Jessie Bourquin Landscape Projects
      - Student Publications Building, 1935-1937 (Box 3)
      - Mr. and Mrs. Alexander Dow, 1935-1937 (Box 3)
      - Mr. and Mrs. Alexander Dow, 1938-1939 (Box 3)
      - Dr. and Mrs. Paul Barker, 1938 (Box 3)
      - Dr. and Mrs. F. Bruce Fralick, 1938 (Box 3)
      - Dr. and Mrs. Bradley Patten, 1937-1938 (Box 3)
      - President and Mrs. Ruthven, 1938 (Box 3)
      - Professor and Mrs. Clifford Woody, 1937-1938 (Box 3)
      - Dr. and Mrs. John Alexander, 1939 (Box 3)
      - Martha Cook Dormitory, 1939 (Box 3)
      - Folio Albums of Projects, 2 volumes (Box 3)
  - Alice Bourquin
    - Scrapbook and Photo Album (Box 3)
  - Alice and Jessie Bourquin
    - Jessie Phillips (mother) Graduation Photograph, 1905 (Box 4)
    - Bourquin sisters and others, undated (Box 4)
    - Slides for American Society of Landscape Architects Fellowships, 1989 (Box 4)
    - Album of Baby Pictures, 1910-1913 (Box 4)
    - Album of Travel Pictures and Postcards, Florida, 1938 (Box 4)
    - Album of Landscape Projects and Gardens, undated (Box 4)
    - Album of Travel Pictures and Postcards, Europe, 1930s (Box 4)
    - Album of Garden pictures, undated (Box 4)
  - James Bourquin (brother)
    - Construction and other photographs accumulated during World War II service of Nazi public buildings, 1935-1940 (Box 4)
  - Slides (in slide boxes)
    - Hillwood subdivision, 1968-1980 (Box 5)
    - Travel and professional, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
    - Travel and personal, 1961-1962; 1980 (Box 5)
    - Travel and personal, 1950s-1971 (Box 5)
    - Travel and personal, 1973-1980 (Box 5)
    - Personal and Hillwood, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Travel and personal, 1963-1965 (Box 6)
    - Travel and personal, 1966-1968 (Box 6)
    - Jessie Bourquin views of home-grounds and gardens developed by her in Ann Arbor and Flint, 1940 (Box 6)
    - Alice Bourquin-ASLA highway slides, 1940s; 2 boxes (Box 6)
    - Lantern slides of gardens and plantings in Ann Arbor and elsewhere in Michigan (Box 7)
  - Negatives of photographs (Box 7)
  - Motion pictures (Box 7)